Guide to the Jess T. Dugan photographs, 2006-2017 RL.11524
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Jess T. Dugan photographs
2006-2017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University)
Dugan, Jess T.
RL.11524
3.0 Linear Feet 2 boxes 58 prints
Collection comprises two bodies of documentary work by photographer Jess T. Dugan. The first comprises 40 large color digital photographs of transgender and non-conforming people over the age of fifty, living throughout the United States. The portraits are of single individuals as well as couples, and were chiefly taken in outdoor and street locations. These portraits are part of an interdisciplinary project titled "To Survive on this Shore: Photographs and Interviews with Transgender and Gender Non-Conforming Older Adults." The second series, "A Moment Collected: Photographs at the Harvard Art Museum," offers 18 black-and-white portraits of staff at the Harvard Museum of Art, taken from 2006-2008 as the museum prepared for a major move and renovation. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke Unviversity.
58 prints
Biographical Note
Jess T. Dugan is an artist whose work explores issues of gender, sexuality, identity, and community. Dugan holds an MFA in Photography from Columbia College Chicago, a Master of Liberal Arts in Museum Studies from Harvard University, and a BFA in Photography from the Massachusetts College of Art and Design.
Dugan's work has been exhibited internationally at the Smithsonian National Portrait Gallery, the Aperture Foundation, the San Diego Museum of Art, and other institutions. Her photographs are in the permanent collections of the Museum of Fine Arts, Boston, the Museum of Fine Arts, Houston, the Harvard Art Museums, and others.
In 2016, Dugan was honored as a Commended Artist by the Smithsonian National Portrait Gallery in Washington, D.C. for her photograph Self-Portrait (Muscle Shirt), exhibited in The Outwin 2016: American Portraiture Today. For her work in this collection, Dugan was awarded the Archive of Documentary Arts 2017 Collection Award for Women Documentarians.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research. Images may only be used for educational, non-commercial purposes; any other use requires the photographer's permission.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Jess T. Dugan photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2017 and 2019.
Scope and Contents
Collection consists of two bodies of documentary work by photographer Jess T. Dugan.
The first, entitled "To Survive on this Shore," comprises 40 large color inkjet photographs of transgender and gender non-conforming people over the age of 50, living throughout the United States. These portraits are part of an interdisciplinary project titled "To Survive on this Shore: Photographs and Interviews with Transgender and Gender Non-Conforming Older Adults." They portray single individuals as well as couples, chiefly in outdoor settings such as parks and streets. All images measure roughly 15 x 20 inches. The interviews conducted for the project are not included in this collection. For this work, Dugan received the 2017 Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Women Documentarians.
The second series, "A Moment Collected: Photographs at the Harvard Art Museum," offers 18 black-and-white portraits of staff at the Harvard Museum of Art, taken from 2006-2008 as the museum and its employees prepared for a major move and renovation. The prints form a 2011 limited-edition portfolio and are housed in a custom hinged portfolio box with accompanying textual narrative.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Art museums -- Photographs; Aging -- United States; Gays -- Portraits; Gay couples -- Portraits; Gender identity -- United States; Homosexuality -- United States; Museums -- Employees -- Portraits; Older gays -- United States; Portrait photography -- United States; Sexual minorities -- United States -- Aging; Transgender people -- United States -- Portraits; United States -- Social conditions -- 1990-; Black-and-white photographs; Color prints (photographs); Digital prints; Gelatin silver prints; Inkjet prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Dugan, Jess T.; Harvard Art Museums -- Officials and employees
- To Survive on this Shore, 2013-2017; 1.5 Linear Feet 1 box 40 prints
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  The photographs are Archival Pigment Prints on Hahnemuhle Photo Rag Pearl paper (320 gsm, 100 percent cotton, natural white, pearl-finish). They were produced on an Epson 3880 inkjet printer using UltraChrome K3 ink.
  Scope and Contents
  These 40 color portraits were created as part of an interdisciplinary project titled "To Survive on this Shore: Photographs and Interviews with Transgender and Gender Non-Conforming Older Adults," by Jess T. Dugan, photographer, and Vanessa Fabbre, PhD, LCSW, a social worker and Assistant Professor at Washington University in St. Louis, whose research focuses on the intersection of LGBTQ issues and aging. Subjects are single individuals as well as couples, chiefly in outdoor settings. All images measure roughly 15 x 20 inches. For this work, Jess Dugan received the 2017 Archive of Documentary Arts Award for Women Documentarians.
  A selection of these photographs was exhibited at the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library's photograph gallery from February 23-June 2, 2019.
  From the artist's statement: "Our society is experiencing a breakthrough moment with respect to transgender issues. From Amazon's series 'Transparent,' winning Golden Globe and Emmy awards, to Caitlyn Jenner's highly publicized transition, transgender issues are getting mainstream exposure in an unprecedented way. However, it is essential to continue educating ourselves and others about the challenges faced by the transgender community and to resist Hollywood-dominated narratives about trans experiences. We believe that the time is right to make this work on a national scale and that society is ready to receive it more than at any other time in history. Ultimately, it is our intention to provide visibility to a community that is often overlooked, both because of their age as well as their gender, and to encourage empathy, understanding, and dialogue."
  - Aidan, 52, Burien, WA, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0001)
  - Alexis, 64, Chicago, IL, 2014 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0002)
  - Barbara, 70, Long Island, NY, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0003)
  - Bobbi, 83, Detroit, MI, 2014 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0004)
  - Bobbie, 60, Hanford, CA, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0005)
  - Bobbie holding a family photo from before her transition, Hanford, CA, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0006)
  - Caprice, 55, Chicago, IL, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0007)
  - Cassandra, 50, San Diego, CA, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0008)
  - Chris, 52, Boston, MA, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0009)
  - Debbie, 61, and Danny, 66, St. Joseph, MO, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0010)
  - Dee Dee Ngozi, 55, Atlanta, GA, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0011)
  - D'Santi, 54, Santa Fe, NM, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0012)
  - Duchess Milan, 69, Los Angeles, CA, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0013)
  - Gloria, 70, Chicago, IL, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0014)
  - Grace, 56, Boston, MA, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0015)
  - Hank, 76, and Samm, 67, North Little Rock, AR, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0016)
  - Hank's hats, North Little Rock, AR, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0017)
  - Helena, 63, Chicago, IL, 2013 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0018)
  - Jamie, 69, and Sherry, 60, Boulder, CO, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0019)
  - Jay, 59, New York, NY, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0020)
  - Joanne, 90, Long Island, NY, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0021)
  - John, 69, Mt. Ida, AR, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0022)
  - Jude, 75, Yuba City, CA, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0023)
  - Jude holding a picture of himself at age 32, Yuba City, CA, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0024)
  - Kendrah, 72, Boston, MA, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0025)
  - Lee Anne, 64, McClellanville, SC, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0026)
  - Leon, 55, St. Louis, MO, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0027)
  - Louis, 54, Springfield, MA, 2014 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0028)
  - Miss Major, 74, Oakland, CA, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0029)
  - Mitch, 55, Seattle, WA, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0030)
  - Preston, 52, East Haven, CT, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0031)
  - Rosalind, 65, New York, NY, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0032)
  - Sky, 64, Palm Springs, CA, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0033)
  - Sky, 64, and Mike, 55, Palm Springs, CA, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0034)
  - SueZie, 51, and Cheryl, 55, Valrico, FL, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0035)
  - Sukie, 59, New York, NY, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0036)
  - Tony, 67, San Diego, CA, 2014 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0037)
  - Tracie, 65, San Diego, CA, 2017 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0038)
  - Vanessa, 51, Atlanta, GA, 2016 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0039)
  - Willy, 52, Oakland, CA, 2015 (Box 1, Image RL.11524-P-0040)
- A Moment Collected: Photographs at the Harvard Art Museum, 2006-2008, 2011
  Series contains 18 gelatin silver prints of Harvard Art Museum staff, shot between 2006-2008 as the Museum prepared for a major move and renovation. Each print is signed, titled, and numbered on the verso.
  The prints are housed in a custom hinged portfolio box created by Jim Di Marcantonio of Hope Bindery in Pawtucket, Rhode Island, and are accompanied by a title page, list of images, and a colophon. This is a limited edition portfolio, number 3/10, created in 2011.
  From the artist's statement: "In 2008, the Harvard Art Museum closed its doors to the public for a major building renovation, scheduled to take five years. Though the renovation was structurally necessary and long overdue, it also brought with it the ending of an era, completely changing a building that had remained largely untouched since 1927. Made in the two years prior to its closing, these photographs portray the people and the spaces of the museum during a time of impending change."
  "By examining a group of people united by their desire to surround themselves with art, these photographs ask larger questions about the desire we all have to live a life full of meaning. In addition, they speak to the passing of time, the idea of change, and the impermanent and fluid nature of each person's involvement in a much larger existence."
  Photographs are gelatin silver prints produced by the artist on archivally processed Ilford Warmtone, glossy fiber-based paper.
  - Mary Correia, Custodian, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0041)
  - Anna Kovacs, Project Coordinator, Collections Move, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0042)
  - Jon Roll, Installer, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0043)
  - Rodney Brown, Security Guard, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0044)
  - Michael Dumas, Staff Assistant, Agnes Mongan Center, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0045)
  - Pippa Eccles, Study Room Assistant, Agnes Mongan Center, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0046)
  - Carol Snow, Conservator, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0047)
  - Jill Comer, Installer, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0048)
  - Michelle Lamuniere, Assistant Curator of Photography, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0049)
  - Al Correia, Crew Chief, Custodial, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0050)
  - Susan Dackerman, Curator of Prints, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0051)
  - Tom Lentz, Director, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0052)
  - Eddie Casay, Janitor, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0053)
  - Maureen Donovan, Registrar and Director of Collections Management, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0054)
  - Deborah Martin Kao, Curator of Photography, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0055)
  - Joanna Karlgaard, Curatorial Assistant, Print Department, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0056)
  - Mark Cosgrove, Assistant Building Superintendent, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0057)
  - Katya Kallsen, Museum Fine Art Photographer, 2006-2008 (Box 2, Image RL.11524-P-0058)